you know that's a philosophical question
Stephen right I apologize for going all
philosophy on the
psychologist I'm Angela Duckworth I'm
Steven Dubner and you're listening to no
stupid
questions today on no stupid questions
does Sigman Freud's concept of
sublimation hold up I did love my mother
but I never wanted to marry her well
Freud wouldn't believe you by the way I
know he wouldn't he would say there he
goes coping also how would your life be
different if you knew you were going to
live forever the world would get very
crowded nobody's dying on the other hand
you free up all that space from
cemeteries yeah exactly you start
building
condos Stephen Angela you know you do a
lot of writing and podcasting I would
say these are creative
Pursuits are you sublimating and do you
need me to Define sublimating for you
this is the psychological form of
sublimating and not the chemical form of
sublimating I assume I didn't mean going
from a solid to a gas without bothering
to stop and become a liquid along the
way you could say that you're going
right to gas form and bypassing liquid
you know I wasn't thinking that no I
meant Mike Freud sure so why don't you
tell me what Freud meant by sublimation
well this is what I think Freud meant
you know having not known Freud
personally but Freud had this idea that
pretty much all of human behavior could
be explained by these unconscious
conflicts that we had deep de in our
psyche and that when you had to deal
with the pain of these conflicts like
wanting to marry your mother but not
being able to or wanting to do things
that you couldn't do you would in some
cases have a mature response and some
cases have a less mature response but
they were all coping mechanisms and
sublimation was a coping response that
he would have said was a mature coping
response that was essentially taking
your pain and transforming it primarily
through ART or through creativity or
more recently as Carrie fiser the
actress said it is taking a broken heart
and turning it into art Freud didn't say
that but I think Freud would have
endorsed that so let me say first I did
love my mother but I never wanted a
marrier well Freud wouldn't believe you
by the way I know he wouldn't and I have
my differences with Freud he would say
there he goes coping but now the way you
just describe sublimation is well I
don't know if it's a broader or
different definition from my
understanding of Freud's definition of
it which I thought was more tied to
sexual drive than just pain are you
asking me this question because free
economics radio is such a sexy show and
you're wondering where that comes
from yes of course that's why I was
asking you Stephen no I wasn't asking
that I think Freud had it right that we
have needs and drives and that sometimes
in ways that we're not fully aware of
we're trying to meet them but I don't
think it was all about sex okay so then
are you asking whether something like
writing or a creative thing podcasting
whatever is my form of sublimation or
just whether I kind of believe in
sublimation I am asking you particularly
about your creative process now Freud
would say this is a waste of time
because Freud would say that you can't
ask somebody directly to introspect but
I think Freud was wrong by the way I
think if Freud would have lived long
enough to see modern Psychotherapy he
would have seen that he's wrong so I
would say I do often think about why it
is that I or anyone who is kind of
excited and passionate about doing what
they do where the drive comes from why
is this the thing that I do basically
and why is this thing still drive me to
want to do it after doing it for a long
time and the thing that is what I do is
essentially ask questions in fact the
reason I started a podcast years and
years ago was in part that my favorite
part of reporting and research was often
interviewing and speaking with people
and it's always heartbreaking when you
write a magazine piece or a book the
vast majority of what people
said was cut out just because of the way
the medium of text writing works and so
I really wanted more of the interview
left intact more of the conversation and
the reason I'm so drawn to that is
because the act of asking questions it
does feel like magic in that you know
when I was a kid I was really super
super shy really yeah I mean honestly
I'm still shy some psychologist I am
well I think I fake it pretty well yeah
you do but if you give me the choice
between here's a group of people and you
can go up to them and have a
conversation or you know there's a book
or a bunch of golf balls and and a
fairway to hit I'm always going to go
for the solo thing but one thing about
asking questions cuz my dad was a German
my mom was a writer although not
professionally at all she was a
full-time mom with eight kids but she'd
been a ballerina so she had a kind of
way of looking at the world that had a
creative angle to it and even in my
little family we had a family newspaper
and the thing that I loved about
journalism from the time I was about
three was that it allowed you in some
cases for me forced you to go up to
people and ask them questions that I
simply wouldn't have had the nerve to do
otherwise so all I'm saying is that I
don't know enough about sublimation to
say whether what I do daily is an act of
sublimation but I do know that I love
what I do in part because it is
connected to something that for me was a
dee rooted I don't know if I would call
it pain or suffering necessarily but
something that wanted to be gotten over
and so it's one of the reasons that I'm
most grateful that I get to have a
living based on this thing that is
actually mostly incredibly fun and
scratches an itch that's otherwise
really hard to scratch so I don't know
if it's about marrying my mother in fact
I think it's quite not but I'm probably
doing a whole lot of sublimating without
knowing it your desire to connect with
other people which shy people have as
well as extroverted people have you know
you you kind of found a way you found a
solution which is being a question
asking journalist who gets very intimate
with your subjects you probably also
love that you know the interview has an
end and then you just like okay bye that
was great like so you get to scratch the
itch but you don't have to deal with the
things that you felt uncomfortable with
either at the beginning or the end of
these interactions I also do probably
95% my interviews remotely which means
that I'm in my home or office recording
studio and somebody else is somewhere
else so I don't actually even have to
make eye contact I mean I know how to
make eye contact I've had conversations
with you in person I can replicate
normal human pretty well I'm adaptive in
that way but it's very costly to my
immune system and like I'm exhausted
after an hourlong conversation with some
other human uh even when you're in
journalism mode well that's a whole
other level because not only is it a
conversation with a stranger but your
mind is constantly trying to process and
then get to the next place knowing that
there's a limited amount of time okay so
what's more exhausting you're having an
interview you're kind of processing it a
multiple levels also there like a lot of
information coming in and you're
synthesizing it in real time versus
cocktail party conversation for the same
amount of time with a stranger as well
but now in this very different setting
and it's no longer Stephen the
journalist it's just like Stephen the
cocktail party invite yeah I would say
the cocktail party is more exhausting
only because what you're subtracting is
usually the exhilaration of the
conversation not that every interview is
exhilarating but the conversations in
the podcast aren't just casual
conversations with people I happen to
want to talk to you're trying to find
out information you're trying to learn
something specific about some scenario
or phenomenon or whatever and so you've
got a goal plus you have to factor in if
alcohol is a factor which at cocktail
parties it usually is and in interviews
it's usually not that's a big
instrumental variable honestly in human
interaction so you know maybe I should
drink more while interviewing or
interview more while drinking less at
cocktail parties yeah you could try it
you could try a little experiment yeah
but I feel that as with many questions
that are asked that the person asking
the question really is interested in
answering the question so what about you
I mean for you being a research
psychologist to what degree is that a
form of
sublimation you chose to become a
research psychologist you teach to and
you rate but most people when they think
of a psychologist they think of a
clinical psychologist psychiatrist maybe
or as I like to say a real psychologist
well okay you didn't go that route you
didn't want to engage in therapy or
clinical treatment and you went this way
so is what you do a form of sublimation
and why did you go that route instead of
the clinical route well before I was in
graduate school I remember filling out
the application to go to graduate school
and there was a box that said do you
want clinical training yes or no and I
asked my student to be adviser Marty
Seligman famous psychologist and a
clinical psychologist I said what does
this question me and he said oh well
think of the most boring person you went
to college with do you have a clear
picture of that person in mind okay now
think about being in a small room with
them for 40 hours a week if the answer
is I would love to do that then check
yes right that's literally what he said
that's terrible I mean it's wonderful
but it's terrible so actually I was
pretty prepared to still Check Yes
because he then elaborated like that's
also the box that you check yes if you
really want to help people I was like oh
like that seems like good box for me it
was partly logistical because when you
become a clinical psycholog you have to
do your PhD and then you have to go on
kind of a residency or an internship and
I was already 32 pregnant with my second
daughter I knew we wouldn't be able to
move in four or five years so I thought
that wouldn't be the right move for me
but I will tell you this Stephen I think
in principle I would really have wanted
to be a clinical psychologist and
actually help people directly but also
that I'd be pretty bad at it I'd
probably spend the whole hour talking
about
[Music]
myself be like oh my God that might we
have a story just hold on let me just I
would be a terrible therapist well I
disagree and maybe that's only because
you've had the last whatever a bunch of
years to be doing research that actually
produces insights that I think are
really practical don't overestimate me
okay so am I sublimating in my own
career am I redirecting some inner
attention to some productive and like my
research um I mean is it possible to not
be well let me start by saying I think
Freud was right about a lot of things in
the kind of broadest brush Strokes the
idea that we do a lot of things to avoid
psychological pain I think he was spot
on so I do believe that a lot of things
that I do are defense mechanisms in a
sense right things that avoid pain so I
am sure that in my life that I have been
coping with things like trying to get
needs met but probably the explanations
are a little less exciting than
unresolved sexual conflict and much more
in the realm of like I grew up in a
family where achievement was important
when I was a little girl and my dad
would say things like the meaning of
life is not to be happy the meaning of
life is to be successful so I I think
maybe you could argue that the fact that
I grew up then to like study achievement
and then I am so obviously achievement
oriented in my family I felt anyway like
love was somewhat proportionately Meed
out according to your accomplishments so
you get a little more love the day you
get into Harvard and I think that that
probably did motivate me to please my
father and to be more accomplished maybe
that's a form of sublimation can you
think of other professions that would
have fulfilled you similarly so let's
see I could have become a doctor Freud
said that so much of this happens below
the level of awareness we'll never know
but I think I know why I really didn't
want to become a doctor and that's
because my parents really wanted me to
become a doctor and I was trying to go
Contra stereotype I think partly there
was a point in my life this is like in
my late 20s where I was wrestling with
what to do and I I thought I might want
to be like something in human resources
and in a way HR is very similar to some
pieces of psychology right human impact
yeah and human nature I don't know if I
ever told you this when I quit playing
music that so that was my first
profession I had three things that I
thought I might be not terrible at one
for some reason was financial planner
what because even though I didn't really
know much about the markets and
economics I was really interested in it
and I thought there's so much bad advice
out there that if I could get even
somewhere above terrible it would be
really fun to help people in net
positive right so that was one and I
didn't do that and then I went to grad
school for writing and I thought I would
teach writing in college so I did teach
at Columbia for a year and it was super
exhilarating because the students were
brilliant and I just realized I was way
too selfish I wanted to spend my time on
my writing not on other people's writing
but that was the reason also why I
didn't do number three which is I
thought really hard about becoming a
psychologist a therapist you did I did
what I did not know this and it was
really number one on the list for quite
a while I loved the idea that there was
a methodology and a huge Canon and a
bunch of brilliant people who had spent
their entire lives and careers in
research trying to figure out how people
think the way they do how to change
patterns habits etc etc I thought
wouldn't it be wonderful to read that
for several years and then help people
with that understanding but I quickly
came to the conclusion as did you that I
would not want to be in that room with
that person for more than like five
minutes just out of selfishness I think
we're not nice enough I think you're
actually quite nice maybe we we don't
have the um patience the temperament can
I just say in defense of us most of the
therapists I know are some of the
wooliest bundle of anxieties neurosis
misplaced dreams and so on so cuz the
way you were describing why we would
fail was because basically we're not the
angels that therapists are and I'm just
here to say that many of the therapists
I know and they would be the first to
admit it they're not the Angels either
yeah that's fair enough okay they're
just human but I don't know if this
counts as fraudi and sublimation but you
do get to scratch the itch of connecting
with people and exploring human nature I
frankly have no plausible explanation
for your desire to be a financial
planner but U everything else fits it
question what is the opposite of
sublimation going directly from a gas to
a solid without passing through liquid
well okay so if you want to take the
Freudian hierarchy of defenses right
from the most mature which is
sublimation but there are also some
others uh humor altruism you know like
turning your pain not being able to have
a child and then for example spending a
lot of your energy in charity work for
mothers or something that would be
altruism and then there were the
immature defenses which were other
coping mechanisms that had the effect of
like kind of getting you into more
trouble right so narcissism denial
famously passive aggression I mean
people use this term vernacularly
without probably even knowing that
that's Freudian in its Origins you
haven't named a thing that I don't have
so I I guess I'm thinking that if I'm
sublimating I'm not doing it well enough
as a financial planner you might want to
move some of your assets out of the
narcissism and passive aggression into
the sublimation column yeah that might
be a better way to invest your
psychological energy I'm going to make a
note to call my broker on Monday sell
narcissism buy some sublimation I
appreciate that Sage advice yeah yeah
hope I get a commission on
that still to come on no stupid
questions every time I take a nap which
is every day do you just say goodbye to
everyone in case I usually nap at my
office where I'm alone with my dog and
I'll say see you later fief or at least
I hope
[Music]
so Angela my question for you today is
this so not many people look forward to
death even if they've lived a long and
satisfying life so it would seem as if
there's a big appetite for the opposite
of death or immortality a lot of
scientists are working on if not
immortality per se say at least ending
Life by many years but here's my
question for you isn't life precious in
large part because it is so finite and
if there were an Avenue toward
immortality how desirable would you find
that you know that's a philosophical
question Stephen right I apologize for
going all philosophy on the psychologist
that's okay I can go there but I make
clear that this is not a question that
has an empirical answer well fair enough
it's not a quite an empirical question
but I'm asking how desirable would you
find the notion of immortality uh me
personally yeah and obviously
extrapolation is welcome I'm kind of
torn because I think about death a lot
actually and if you ask anybody who
knows me well they will completely back
me up on this I bring it up a lot I'm
always calculating like how many years
it's likely that I'll live and then I go
around the table and I just look at
people and I'm like and you're not going
to be here in 50 years like no way
knowing you as I do and based on some
past conversations we've had I'm
guessing the reason that you think about
death all the time is because you are
driven to accomplish a lot and you don't
want to waste time is that the idea or
is there some other reason yeah I mean
because I know my life has an end and
that the end is you know is nigh I mean
still blink of an eye in this sort of
grand scheme of things when I think
about my own mortality I experienced a
sense of urgency like oh you know those
eight things on my to-do list I better
get them done who knows how long I have
left I can see other people who would
have a different reaction right if you
said look your life is a blink of the
eye they would say I'm going out to
dinner immediately so I have had my
priorities accentuated but when I was in
high school I think it was in high
school there was a book that came out
called how we die it actually got me on
this whole thing where I started reading
like all these books like that be not PR
so fiction non-fiction I went on a death
spree in a way just reading about you
know the mechanics of death and my
summary conclusion was that death itself
wasn't as frightening to me as dying
dying seemed to unequivocally suck I was
like o dying sounds awful you know
painful
terrifying death is just the absence of
life and you know you're not there
anyway it's a long nap it's a long nap
from which you don't wake up yeah but
when you're napping you don't know that
you're going to wake up either that's
true do you I don't every time I take a
nap which is every day do you just say
goodbye to everyone in case I do say
goodbye to the dog you know I usually
nap at my office where I'm alone with my
dog and I'll say see you later fief or
at least I hope so yeah but let me go
back to the original question the most
interesting word I've ever heard applied
to human life was when I had a
conversation once with Steve Lev my
Freakonomics friend and co-author who
you know and we were talking about the
value of a human life and he said very
casually as if it were not a profound
thought but I found it really profound
he said well to everyone the value of
their own life is infinite and I thought
that was a really good way of putting it
because there is almost nothing that
most of us would not do to save or
extend our own lives there are many
cases in which we will go to Great
Lengths to extend or save someone else's
life but the notion of infinite as the
value that we place on our own lives
struck me as resonant and I began to
think about that and then you begin to
think about other things that are
infinite you know I got to think about
like well let's say you like M&M's let's
say you have a barrel of M&M's what
seems to be a bottomless barrel and the
way you treat that resource is going to
be very different than if you have one
bag of M&Ms and so to me the notion of
death and immortality is constrained by
the fact that a there's uncertainty and
B it is finite and so I got to thinking
well what if you told me that I would
live till Infinity What would life feel
like and I don't think it would feel
very good and I wondered well how much
of that is just because it's so
different and how much of it is because
it no longer has infinite value because
it actually is infinite okay well I'm
going to argue against that I think that
you know for sure scarcity heightens
value in every possible way like hey
this is the last &m on the planet
suddenly that becomes more valuable than
if there's an infinite number of M&M's
this is the last day of vacation well
that's different than like vacation is
going to stretch on really frankly as
long as you want it to I agree that
scarcity heightens value but I don't
think it's the only thing that makes
something valuable and just to answer
your question directly if it's a
multiple choice between immortality and
just living my life I guess as it's
being lived right now with an end yeah
of course I would pick immortality I
want to live forever and I don't think
that the value of the days that I would
be living of course an infinite number
of them would go to zero or even be
negative because I don't have that boost
from scarcity because there are other
things that make your day valuable or
even pleasurable that don't depend on
scarcity so I like your answer much
better than mine good you can change it
if you want okay so let's say I change
it and let's say I too want to live
forever keep each other company now my
next question for you becomes how would
my or your life be fundamentally
different if you knew you were going to
live forever because I can't imagine it
wouldn't be wildly different first of
all just think of how longlasting your
friendships and relationships would be
yeah I've known him 850
Years also the world would get very
crowded nobody's dying on the other hand
you free up all that space from
cemeteries yeah exactly right you could
start building condos but okay so how
would I live my life differently I think
the way children live their lives is in
a way kind of like the way somebody
would live their life if they were
Immortal right cuz they are really not
thinking about their impending doom and
that means I think two things one is the
obvious thing which is they are able to
be carefree and in the moment and not
have the future weigh on them that's
kind of the obvious stereotype of how
children are but the other thing that
children do which I think is very
interesting is they invest a lot in
learning and I think it's
developmentally adaptive if you are a
creater who does have a lifespan of X
years that at the very beginning of Life
where you can get a lot of return on
investment on your learning you invest a
lot in learning whereas later on who
knows I might only have 6 seconds left
you know you're not signing up for cor
era by the way there's this whole theory
in Psychology called Terror management
Theory and it's the idea that we have
this conundrum as human beings uniquely
which is that like all other animals we
want to avoid death we try to survive
but unlike all other animals we have
conscious awareness of our impending
mortality and this is terrifying I've
read that a million times it's one of
the many many different things that
people say when you ask them what is the
one thing that distinguishes humans from
all other their animals we use the fork
we make jokes right there are million
that you know most of which are not
really very accurate but one of them is
that which is we know we're going to die
and I think it's a little presumptuous
to not assume that animals know they're
going to die if only because a sometimes
you feel like you're going to die but B
animals have seen other animals die like
they lie down and don't get up and are
they so dumb that they don't understand
that that's something different than
life I think that one could certainly
make the case that animals have seen
death probably they've seen death more
than humans have depending on the animal
but I do think you could make the
argument that human beings have a
certain kind of metacognitive awareness
like you can see lots of animals die but
not kind of make the connection that you
two are going to die and then also like
just to ponder that and I'm not sure
that animals have that sophisticated
level even Consciousness people have
argued is uniquely human the major
prediction from Terror management Theory
is that you know we have these
unconscious coping mechanisms for ways
to deal with this anxiety that are not
obvious so when people try to bolster
their self-esteem or reaffirm their
worldview like their belief in the
afterlife for example that is really
just a way of dealing with the anxiety
of knowing you're going to die the
notion of the afterlife goes back a long
long long time into our most ancient
traditions and from my reading of it it
was both let's say an incentive right
toward living a virtuous life but also a
means to respond to the uncertainty of
death because it was just so you know
disturbing as it still is for many
people in fact I don't know if the
Ancients were any more disturbed by
death than we are because we're so
removed from Death now we do seem to be
pretty good at like not really thinking
about it too much right yeah and you
know there has been a lot written about
including the Sherwin nulan book you
mentioned earlier how we die about how
modern society but modern America in
particular has just removed death from
life it's made a separate quarantined
chapter which is left to Specialists you
know it used to be you would be buried
by your family you know your body would
be watched over by your loved ones we
had rituals yeah yeah and there is
somewhat of a return to that is there
how well there are people who promote
and offer kind of home burials and green
burials and things like that it is a
movement but a small one but even
cremation has grown a ton in the last I
guess three four five decades so I think
there are a lot of rituals that are
shifting now people wanting to get away
from the formality of what has been for
the last you know 100 or so years but I
do feel that as I get older and everyone
around me obviously gets older at the
same rate turns out yeah isn't that wild
as far as I know we might have to start
carbon dating some of these people I
know because they seem to go much much
faster yes but it does strike me that
thinking and talking about death which
is mostly considered a gruesome and off
limits thing is to me primma fascia not
gruesome and should not be off limits
and so maybe me asking you about it in
the guise of immortality was not the
best way to go maybe what I really just
wanted to talk about with you was death
but the beauty part is you're so good
that you took my question about
immortality and May about death and so
you helped me manage my Terror just a
little bit I really appreciate that
Angie yeah well you're welcome
Sten no stupid questions is part of the
Freakonomics radio network this episode
was produced by me Rebecca Lee Douglas
and now here's a fact check of today's
conversations during the conversation
about sublimation Angela references a
quote by the late actress Carrie fiser
this quote was actually never shared
publicly by fiser it was made famous by
Merill stre as part of her cesil B
demill acceptance speech at the Golden
Globes in
2017 Streep and fiser had become friends
after Streep starred in Postcards From
The Edge the movie version of Fischer's
semi-autobiographical book stre shared
the quote as a way to honor fiser after
her recent death which had occurred less
than 2 weeks prior to the awards
ceremony the full quote is this as my
friend the dear departed Prin Leia said
to me once take your broken heart make
it into art later on in the episode
Angela shares that as a young woman she
was very interested in reading and
learning about death she thought she
first read Sherwin B Nan's how we die
while she was in high school the book an
attempt to demythologize the process of
dying actually came out in 1994 when
Angela was in her early 20s so she
wouldn't have had access to it as a
teenager finally Steven mentions the
rise of Home burials green burials and
cremation there aren't many statistics
available on home burials which are
burials where friends and family prepare
the body and service by themselves but
if you own your own land you can bury a
deceased family member on it in every
state but California Indiana Washington
and the District of Columbia green
burials however are certainly On The
Rise according to a 2018 survey by the
National Funeral Directors Association
72% of cemeteries report an increase in
green burial demand the process can be
as simple as wrapping the deceased in a
shroud and lowering them into the ground
until about 150 years ago what we now
call a green burial was simply known as
a burial cremation is also becoming
increasingly popular in 2016 cremation
became the most popular method of body
disposal in the United States over overt
taking in tubement for the first time I
personally think that cremation is
pretty cool because you have so many
options with the ashes you can use them
to plant a tree or create Diamond
Jewelry you can transform them into
artificial reefs for marine life and if
you have
$2500 you can even shoot them into space
unfortunately cremation isn't considered
green because the process emits as much
carbon dioxide as a THM car trip that's
it for the fact check
no stupid questions is produced by
Freakonomics radio and Stitcher our
staff includes Allison craigo Greg rien
James Foster and Karen Wallace our theme
song is and she was by Talking Heads
special thanks to David burn and Warner
Chapel Music if you'd like to listen to
our show ad free subscribe to Stitcher
premium you can also follow us on
Instagram and Twitter at nsq show and on
Facebook at nsq show and if you heard
Steven or Angela refer to something that
you'd like to know more about we provide
links to all the books and studies
Concepts and names that they drop each
episode just go to freakonomics.com
nsq thanks for
[Applause]
listening I don't know how to answer
your question super directly but let me
try to answer it at least parallel if
that's a word well that's a lot of L's
and four L's and five letters wow I was
going to say if it's a word it's over
the quota on
L's Stitcher